hi welcome back to lomrim
and welcome back translators you are
amazing
especially the ones from romania
christian you guys
you guys are amazing and
oola thank you all right
here we go we're gonna start back on the
alarm room
we have a busy day today
it's the last day of the program and
we'll start
uh with the tibetan here today
what is the jewel that you should keep
in your hand
what's the most beautiful thing you
should keep practicing all day
it's this idea of going to meet your mom
on the other planets okay all right we
practiced it yesterday
la some people say
um the core
of my practice the thing i hold in the
palm of my hand
is like some high tantric practice you
know i don't know medicine buddha tara
amitabha okay kachi gyana
kaktok is like uh it's like eating or
something it's
some kind of magic magic book about uh
you know how to make your business go
better
like magic book or something like that
number magic
number book something like that uh
kam chen nabo there's also this
there are these funny little books like
uh how to stop
the dharmi for stopping
bad lawsuits against you okay
kamchu means lawsuit so uh
these are weird little books okay
so this kind of darwini which is just
for
worldly thing right i i don't want i
want to win this bankruptcy suit
so i'm going to find this special day
you know
so glad chase there so people told
the llama pablo they said
that's my practice i'm focusing on
stopping bankruptcy lawsuits you know
with mantras you know and he said come
on
champions
okay it's too bad you don't have the
enough good karma
to hear about bodhichitta or you
wouldn't do those things
okay
and if you keep focusing on these
strange little
mantras like how to stop a lawsuit then
you're never going to get to buddhahood
okay all right cho sterling
llama number two lord artisa
who is one of the most famous teachers
in the history of buddhism in asia
somebody asked him who was your greatest
teacher
and he said ser lingbah okay
su wanna
and then they said why and they said he
taught me bodhichitta
he taught me bonita chuknyung cup drama
kiss samsung
dilla chin lopki and when
whenever lord artesha got sick like if
lord atesha got
gout in his foot he would call drum
tingey
and say come touch my foot he would ask
his disciple
his favorite disciple come touch hey hey
jig man come touch my foot
you know and then he said drums and just
say why and he and atisha said
you have the most bodhichitta anybody i
know you know
so can you hey and it's weird for a
teacher to ask their student
to heal them so the
pabong quebec is saying look it's it's
important
that atisha this great great llama
used to call his student to come touch
his foot
because the student had bought each
other okay all right
this indirectly this
is lord artesha praising bodhichitta
okay
hundred dollar question who is there
wait who got it first was tim on the way
were you on the way
fifty dollars each okay kelsey and tim
he's the one who wrote uh the crown of
knives please
all right which is uh
a text that our dci vice president seji
orel takahashi is translating
it was written a thousand years ago
dharmarakshita was whose teacher
atisha okay he's lord atisha's teacher
his other teacher okay the one who not
from the golden island right
all right and and he wrote this
incredible book
by the way uh
in china's soft power program next
weekend
we'll be studying the diamond cutter
business book
and we reached the correlations the 46
correlations
uh we reached the most important part
of the old diamond cutter business book
in this it's a vip program for chinese
executives okay and that part
talks about correlations if you do this
you're going to get done if you do this
you're going to get done okay where does
that come from
i stole it from dharmalakshita okay
i stole it from sage's text by the way
seji and his wife noor
are making a beautiful book called the
peacock warrior
which mixes rumi and dharmarakshita
these two great poets okay so look out
for this book
i'm sure diamond cutter press is going
to publish it diamond cutter press by
the way
can we talk about that
speaking about the press which publishes
all of our translations
i'm very happy to announce
two days ago at diamond mountain
i received from yali
in taiwan this amazing
book published by diamond cutter press
and yali in taiwan here it is
okay if you need exercise
buy this book okay it's very good
for for you don't have to do yoga you
just
lift up the book uh every day a couple
times okay this is a
a new edition of the two most important
sutras in the world the heart sutra and
the
diamond color sutra and this is the
greatest
explanation of that
of those two sutras by
okay and uh this is a collector's
edition
okay that you can
and you get up this one and you open up
this one and
you can get enlightened and exercise at
the stake
at the same time
okay yeah so you can get these two books
if you like uh here's the information
from the press for this is the diamond
cutter press
and there's the general
books that they carry next one next
picture
uh this is if you want to order the
sponsor edition okay
and we are offering it for a special
extra prize so you can support the
translators yay
okay that's called a dharma discount
where we charge you more so you can
support the translators
all right don't forget
the mixed nuts translators they got a
new virus
called babies we got
we got amelie we got
my tree that's why you have to buy these
books
all right thank you guys let's go back
to the
text all right that was slick right i
[Music]
who wrote that book that sage is
translating
he used to be abhidhamma he used to be
he started out as an abhidharma teacher
okay and then he got interested in
in the bodhichitta teachings okay at
some point
he got interested in the bodhichitta
teachings and he switched to
middleweight
okay because of the bodhichitta
teachings he got
because of the bodhisattva teaching to
god
this great great abhidharma scholar
switched to middleweight because he
learned how to love people
okay yay and you can see a peacock
warrior here i like to call him the
peacock warrior
hundred dollars why is peacock important
because they
eat the poison and yeah hundred dollars
for janice
uh peacocks
the thing that makes their feathers
such a beautiful color is they like to
eat
plants that would kill other animals
okay what's the what's the analogy
alex the analogy is that bodhisattva is
able to
take the pain that would
down the rest of us and turn it into
something beautiful in the world
yeah bodhisattvas take trouble and turn
it into something
beautiful cool buddhist office don't run
away from
tense situations they look for them
and they jump in and they make them
better
okay they don't run away from problems
they look for problems
and they jump in okay that's a kind of
buddhist
chitter okay all right
is amazing because he was equally famous
in central china and in tibet okay
his his teaching spread throughout asia
why two reasons shenian denzel for a
hundred dollars i'm in a good mood this
morning
shane and tenso yeah how to take a
teacher
okay how to how to follow a teacher
number one hundred dollars for jake may
give me a hundred dollars
okay he was so good at
respecting his teacher studying with his
teacher
the karma of that made him famous
throughout asia his teaching
spirituality
and because of his bodhichitta okay
those two things
right goddamn commission is something
[Music]
well we're the third or something uh
tomkapa is considered the new kadampas
and the kadampas are the early buddhists
of tibet and they were
mostly hippies with families
and they had little dharma centers just
like
nowadays okay
they used to say septimena if you don't
have bloody tuna
and you just have meditation how good is
your meditation
you want the modern version or the
ancient version
the ancient version is someone can take
a
tibetan religious drum and
during your meditation they can carry it
and put it next to your head
and go and you don't even hear it
okay what's the modern version
french fries you can't put french fries
in front of the meditator
and they don't smell anything that's how
good is your meditation okay
then the early kadampa said i don't care
if your meditation is so good
that you can't hear jimmy hendrix
at full volume or smell french fries
from mcdonald's in front of your nose if
your meditation is that good
i don't care if you don't have
bodhichitta i'm not interested then
you're not a meditator
okay i don't care if you can focus so
well
that i can play jimi hendrix in your ear
and you don't hear it
okay all right yo young machine you
ain't got nowhere you didn't go anywhere
okay
then there's a llama named rahula gupta
who was a a teacher of atisha actually
and he said i don't care if you saw
medicine buddha face to face
i don't care if you can read other
people's mind
i don't care if you can do magic i don't
care
if your meditation
is as strong as the himalayan mountains
not moving right unshakable as
as mount everest i don't care if you
don't have bodhichitta
you didn't go anywhere you didn't go
anywhere okay
all right that's atisha's teacher his
other teacher
[Music]
is for us what the wheel is for a
real emperor okay you define
the president of the world in buddhism
by his or her wheel
her spaceship her flying saucer okay
and you define a buddhist by their buddy
chili
a buddhist without buddha children is
like a real emperor without a
wheel or
a person without life
okay it's like a dead corpse okay
a buddhist without bodhichitta
is like i don't know a baseball player
who died
without life they're as useful as a
baseball player
who died yesterday got it
kind of funny all right or
lakba means or like a football player
without a
leg or without an arm you guys come on
it's it's useless
okay okay emperor's flying sausage you
guys
guys got my flying saucer
these things are real apparently
okay yeah
who are you i'm a
king of the world what's your nickname
flying saucer emperor
hey where's your flying saucer i never
got one
okay that's a buddhist with our buddhism
okay
all right um sorry
lamale uh by the way this is the uttara
tantra
of uh who maitreya
okay we started it many years ago in
tucson
then they started talking about pat
paternity and maternity okay paternity
and maternity okay dads and moms
okay and maitreya says
the relationship of buddy chitter
and wisdom is like your mom
and your dad okay your wisdom
is your mom your buddy chitta
is your dad and your dad has to make
your mom
pregnant that's a beautiful image
okay your bodhichitta
has to make your emptiness pregnant okay
you need both
you need to get a kid you got to have a
dad
somebody was asking me veronica said why
is it that the dad works for five
minutes
and then he gets visiting rights for the
rest of his life
you know i'm not getting into that uh
but i can say you kind of need him
for a while uh at the beginning
okay so anyway the dad is being compared
to
in the long run the that is compared to
bodhichitta
and the mom is compared to emptiness
understanding
and body cheddar has to make a baby in
the emptiness and understanding it's a
beautiful image to think about
okay uh pani ricky
so the father has a special role for a
brief time especially
but the mother is around all the time
and she has a long-term role
changes
the unique cause of a buddha is
bodhichitta the father
just you
and we call the understanding
emptiness not unique because of
tatwa buddha for a hundred dollars
why did we talk about buddha it was to
explain why
some a certain buddha isn't can be not a
buddha and still be a buddha
hat buddhas are still buddhas because
they boot
they tap a bud got it
so that's more common understanding
emptiness
is shared by those three tracks
but bodhichitta is unique right only
higher training
but each it is like the dad who drops by
for a while and then emptiness
understand is like the mom
who has to stay there the whole life and
keep producing got it
all right
you can talk about mahamudra okay
like some kind of super tantra
and you can talk about zog chen
you know it's a kind of weird you know
super secret thing okay or you could
talk about
kirim and zoryam the two levels okay you
can talk talk talk okay
fatso mambo sheltoma you can say you met
tara
in 20 21 taurus this morning okay
but if you really want to get to
buddhahood quickly
drop those and focus on bodhichin drop
those
visions of taran the 21 angels drop this
uh
what do you call mahamudra this the
weird maha mudra
dropped that weird zoktin just focus on
loving other people you
you be farther ahead okay all right
that's what he says temba that's not me
that's
pablanca okay
this teaching is the essence of
everything artichoke ever taught
you guys
somebody
don't put your hopes in meeting some
like
tantric buddha tomorrow or something
like that just relax
and practice the seven steps
of getting to bodhichitta which we're
going to study next
in the future norman okay all right and
he says
that's the ultimate donor bodhichitta
is the ultimate mantra okay recite
bodhichitta in your heart
that's the ultimate mantra okay all
right then
we checking you like
and it's worth the hard work it's gonna
take
okay it's worth the hard work
it's gonna take to get to bodhichitta
it's worth it
if it takes you 12 years it's worth it
okay
[Music]
it's worth your time and i'll tell you
some good news okay he says i'll tell
you some good news
i like it
[Music]
you want to guess tim for zero dollars
i always offered tim the highest amount
double negative
[Music]
not mickey not kill not not
killer good
if you practice bodhichitta
it's not a thing that can refuse to come
if you if you practice every day
buddha cannot refuse you sorry
bodhichitta cannot refuse you
if you practice every day body tear
cannot refuse you
because that's the nature of cause and
effect
if you plant the cause you will get the
result so just relax
go through the steps of body shadow
study about each other
relax and the nature of reality
is that it will sneak up on you whether
you want it or not
just relax do the meditations we taught
you
and it's gonna come in fact you cannot
stop it
if you didn't want it you couldn't stop
it okay so just relax
plant the cost and wait and it'll come
okay
all right cheso i love it sona nepa sona
nepa if word was here
i could test his knowledge sona nepa
means
the nature of cause and effect is the
nature of cause and effect
so relax the cause and effect
is causing effect so just relax
okay do these meditations and relax
it's the body chit is gonna come up on
you you can't stop it
okay just trust the process
trust the process
there was people in tibet before artesha
showed up who thought
that you were granted bodhichitta by
taking the vows
they thought oh somebody the llama said
i need buddhism
yeah okay so i'll go take the vowels
and then i'll have bodhichitta then
pabonga says
it don't work that way okay it does not
work
it it does work that way for other
vowels what vowels
you just show up you get it and you're
done
vinaya vows okay you show up at the monk
ceremony
you take the vows two minutes later
you're a monk
okay now you go to a bodhichitta
ceremony
you make the commitment are you a
buddhist officer
two two two minutes later he said no no
it don't work that way
it could take 12 years you know okay so
don't you know there were people in
tibet
before they got educated buddhist
educated buddhist is so rare
there are lots of buddhists there are
very few educated buddhists there are
lots of buddhists
there are very few buddhists who know
what the hell they're talking about
okay i don't know how many million
buddhists there are
how many buddhists who know what
buddhism is
but i don't know okay he says
there were these silly people in tibet
before
they got educated about buddhism before
they got really educated about buddhism
and they thought if i go to the
bodhisattva vows ceremony then i'll be a
bunny suffer when i get home
he said no i don't it works that way
with the monk and none spells
but they don't work that way with the
bodhi tuna bells okay but it's tough for
us
and then the guy says no no at the
beginning of the ceremony you say
for all living beings for all mother
living beings he said
that's not bodhichitta that's the
beginning of the ceremony okay
that's just words okay jump at some good
chance i
there were people who thought
if they say those words at the beginning
of the vowel ceremony
then they should have booty chatted by
the end of the vowel ceremony
because at the beginning of the ceremony
it says i'm doing this for all living
beings but he said come on
that's not how it works okay
ballet to get body cheddar
you have to low jump
train the mind okay what does they call
mental mind mind training or something
like that
it sounds like iq improvement course or
something
mental training or men
i forgot there's some really bad
translations of lojo
okay exceptional in their
badness so low junk doesn't mean
to train your brain or something like
that it means
semke to get bodhichitta
it doesn't mean mental development or
something this is a terrible translation
okay
here it is right here changsam
gilla keva lo jong
means you're practicing bodhichitta
you're trying to get bodhichitta
you're going through the seven
steps of reaching bodhichitta
guppane loma jamba sotaki
but it's not like getting
deniable where
five minutes after the monk ceremony
you're a mom okay it's not like that you
gotta work on it
okay all right oh does that mean i
shouldn't take buddy stoppables
come on taking buddies off of else marks
the beginning of your struggle to become
a good person to be
to reach to become a bodhisattva okay
you
you have to take them that's how you
start
that's the way you're supposed to start
but it's not
equal bodhichitta okay all right
this lady in this picture
is taking her i don't know
one-day vows wait is that my
no there we go this lady is taking vows
can you take
can you take buddhist alpha vowels in
front of a plant
yeah why not it's allowed it's allowed
you're allowed to give
bodhisattva vows to yourself that's what
she's doing here
okay so that's why i chose the picture
okay
but that does does that mean she's a
bodhisattva five minutes later
not really okay we can call her an
honorary bodhisattva
okay all right next part
and tim i know i have to stop in eight
minutes okay
i'm watching the clock
oh i did the book advertising
you can't even get a correct
idea of what's bodhichitta
just from the ceremony you see i mean
you can't even see where you have to go
exactly
this is a very very famous piece of
sarcasm from atisha okay
so normally llamas try to be more
positive right
[Music]
but when a llama gets sarcastic you
better watch out
okay so here we go this is one of the
most famous pieces of sarcasm
in all of buddhist scripture okay
here's the attitude okay god
you remember he came to tibet and he's
like you to bends
you guys are awesome you're really
awesome
and they said yeah why this is
you guys sorry
i guess i don't have the karma to be
sarcastic
you guys are so amazing
you know why you got bodhichitta
without love or compassion oh man
you guys are you're so advanced
you know you got to bodhichitta
without learning how to love other
people
and to care about their suffering sheesh
you guys are
much more advanced than the indians got
it
sarcasm okay you you guys
developed a special man to become a
bodhisattva
without loving people and without
worrying about their pain you guys are
awesome
okay i wonder if the guys that he was
talking to
got it some
perky shepherd only tibetan could do
that
[Laughter]
he expressed his displeasure okay
then they asked him what are you trying
to say
and he says it's alarm rim
it's alarm rim you got to do this
then you do this then you do this okay
you get compassion sorry in this
presentation
you get love then you get compassion
then you get bullied chilling okay okay
that was his answer
[Music]
means start with love go to compassion
reach body children okay lo zhong
practice those three steps which is a
segway huge segway
we just finished yay
how cool is buddy cheddar we finished
this section yay
we got to the end of our la rim of
course
congratulations to everybody in the room
everybody
you got to the end of it you now know
how cool is bodhichitta you're supposed
to be hungry too
get it okay and that's the next mommy of
course okay
now let's get a little taste of it okay
let's get a little taste of it we have a
few minutes okay
[Music]
so therefore we're moving on
to how to develop bodhichitta okay we
just spent
you know i don't know how many classes
14 15 classes
convincing you to buy this car
now it's time to put the money down okay
you want the car you want this tesla
with the wings you know
butterfly wings yeah i'll take it all
right now let's talk about how you got
to pay for it okay
changing quebec tsunami there's two
methods
for becoming a bodysub there's two two
tracks you can go either way
okay
and it's gonna involve making a
commitment in a ceremony
okay
okay you're ready say
men not
i'll give you two options to pay for
this car
what's the car but he said i gave you
two options i gave you two options
they are both extremely reasonable
that's my new york accent it's like
venerable tundra
you guys want a coffee okay okay your
first option
is the seven step cause and effect
method to get to become a body stop
to get the body to the seventh step
cause and effect system
six causes one
result six causes one effect it's called
the seven step
cause-and-effect method because by the
way
the effect is body china then there's
six steps you have to do
that's the first way to get body sharing
and we're gonna study that first okay
later we'll study dhakshen yamchai
what's that be careful
it has two parts it has two parts
and jay yeah
first see that other people's right to
happiness
is totally equal to your right to
happiness we have equal right
that's called nyam that's called nyam
everybody in this planet
has an equal right to get what they want
okay
nobody has more right to get what they
want
than other people we all have equal
right
to get what we want we all have equal
to happiness that's the preliminary to
the second method
that's the beginning of the second
method and then j
yeah then switch then switch positions
and by the way
just to let you know it's a very
depressing practice
it's a very depressing practice it is
not
put yourself in cat's shoes so you can
see how she feels
day to day at that mountain it's not
that it's not
this compassionate sweet thing where you
say you know come on geshe-la put
yourself in cat's shoes
try to feel how she feels it's not that
okay
well what is it then it's worse than
none
you put geshe-la's brain
behind venable cutting's eyes
and you look at geshela
and see how he's doing that's the
exchange
and it's and it's bad news
okay you i put my brain
in venerable cuttings head and i
look at geshe michael and see how is he
really
you know is he considerate is he kind
is he thoughtful is he moral does he do
his practices
you know you put your brain in another
person's skull
and you look back at yourself and you
and you see
the bad news okay that's the real second
method so you might want to skip that
one
all right but let's go to the first
method okay we have a few minutes
i have four minutes right tim
hyundai
[Music]
lopez
first step of the first method the
seven-step method
is say
that's where you try to develop an
affection for other people
i like you okay
an affection for other people you just
look at other people and you
you feel like
like you're a mom who's very proud of
her child right
katie does something amazing janice is
feels like a million dollars right
that's affection that's called affection
youngjamba means affection
the the goal in the seven step
method of reaching buddha china
is to start with affection i
like you i just like you okay
i like you all right and it's it's
nothing fancy
it's i like you okay i kind of like you
okay all right that's called you on
jumbo numbers
who followed that system well chanda
kirti who we had a lot of time with him
this
this retreat we spent a lot of time with
chanakyati
and chandragomi uh who's
important for the different vowels and
shanta rakshita who's the teacher of
kamala kamalashira not dharma
shantarakshita okay teacher of
kamalashira okay
and he came to tibet and that's a long
story okay
all right
now as far as equality
and what are we going to call that
second one where i put myself in cat's
head
switching equality and switching you
gotta it's two parts right
nyamjay dakshan yamchai as far as
equality and switching
that was followed by master shantideva
mainly okay
ultimately these two methods
of becoming a bodhisattva have come down
to us
through manjushri and maitreya okay
through manjushri and maitreya
ultimately it's a combination
of two powerful brains
and they were separate for many
centuries the two teachings were
separate
for many centuries and atisha put them
together at
combine them what equality and switching
shantideva system and the seven step
system of atisha okay he he
he joined them he joined them together
okay
he he's the one who of chandragupta he
joined them together
so we're we are called the
confluence of the two rivers
our generation our generation is called
the generation where the two rivers
flow to one into one okay all right
cool uh i'll say one more thing and then
we'll switch over to tim i know tim has
some uh
announcements and things to talk about
uh
and we're gonna do that lottery right
it's a lottery question
right okay uh one more thing
get i'll leave you with a question okay
this is kind of interesting
there's two ways to get the bodhichitta
one is
me i put my head in i put my brain in
cat's head and the other way
is what yeah
seven steps which one do you think was
traditionally more secret
switching yeah switching was more secret
yeah switching was more secret which
one do you think is more inclusive
they say the seven they say the seven
includes the switching but the switching
doesn't necessarily include the seven
okay got it something like that
okay last question then
they will go to the question from the
lottery
for for 300 let's end on a good
let's do a thousand dollars okay last
last question everyone woke up no
that time doesn't matter gestalt go
ahead okay
last question for a thousand dollars but
let me get it straight
[Music]
why should putting myself in cat's head
be more secret than the seven steps for
trying to develop
affection for everybody why should
putting myself in cat's head
be more secret than trying to develop
affection for the people around me
thousand dollars
alex wants to go for it it was so
radical
the idea was so radical and difficult
that people
who tried it might think it was crazy
and give up the teachings all together
nice it's beautiful and it's not correct
anybody else want to try
she said uh it's so radical that it
might freak people out basically and it
is true but it's that's not the answer
i'm looking for
why would me putting myself in cat's
head
be a secret method and then
the affection method would not be so
secret
traditionally it's explained that way
it's pretty it's sitting right in front
of you so obvious
i guess you don't want the money imagine
herself becoming someone else
okay cancel the bet officially i'm
officially canceling the bed
i mean joe you want to take a guess i'll
say it again
no it's a lot of money okay
you do the first one quietly
you don't tell anybody got it
you put yourself in cat's head and you
don't tell cat you don't tell alex you
don't tell janice
you just do it quietly affection you
have to say tam i like you guys
thank you so much for the long room
jordan you're awesome
pao pachi thank you gail save federal
goals if you'll give me two venerables
you're so sufferingable that's affection
affection is expressed honey thank you
for dying mountain joe
thank you for doing all the work for
honey
that's affection affection is expressed
right
but looking at yourself from another
person's eyes
is done quietly okay
right maybe nobody knows you're doing it
okay except that suddenly your behavior
improves
[Laughter]
because you're watching yourself okay
tim
yeah now something happened with this
course um
geshe-la added too much extra stuff
and we didn't get as far as we're
supposed to get okay
why there's a famous segway
there's a famous bridge between
the 10 cool things of bloody chitta
which we just covered
and starting the seven steps there's a
famous
bridge and they introduce it this way
they say would you like to paint
the llama house here right okay
that house built in 1875 the first part
right
uh with we painted it it cost sixty
thousand dollars i remember i
i raised the money i helped raise some
money
uh so
did the guys come with a big paintbrush
and start painting question
no they come with plaster they come with
plaster
because the place looked like a civil
war you know
cannon was shot at it there was holes
there was
cracks there was different parts falling
off
first job when you're gonna paint an old
house
is plaster and make it smooth that's a
famous example
for the seven steps that's a famous
example
you don't paint the llama house
until you plaster it and make it smooth
so the paint will stick anybody want to
guess what that means
you have to make it equal first
yeah first you study equanimity first
you learn to treat everybody equal
okay before you start bodhichitta
you need a mini course in treating
everybody equal
and i i didn't have time to cover it so
guess what
we're gonna have a special two day
mini course about infinite
equanimity infinite equanimity
because you cannot start the seven steps
until you feel the same about everybody
you can't learn
love for people until you catch up
everybody to neutral okay so we're gonna
work on that first so i didn't have time
to cover that
and we're gonna have a special weekend
two day watching majika thing
good sorry of course and tim's tim's
gonna figure it out
okay sometime in the next
in the early summer okay